Zahidur Talukder

Rigorous Design Lab Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering The University of Texas at Arlington 500 UTA Blvd, Arlington, TX 76019 Phone: (682) 266-9164
Email: zahidurrahim.talukder@uta.edu
Web: https://zahid2734.github.io/
Github: https://github.com/Zahid2734
Google Scholar: https://scholar.google.com

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My current research interests span the areas of the theoretical, empirical, and security aspects of machine learning, algorithms, and distributed learning. I have been working on secured and efficient data and client handling of federated learning. I have developed self-regulating clients who can handle data-level errors and new aggregation techniques for servers in federated learning. I am highly passionate about applications involved with privacy-preserving machine learning, algorithms, and distributed learning. My overarching goal is to design and develop applied AI for social good to provide a safe and trustworthy online ecosystem.

EDUCATION

The University of Texas at Arlington, Texas

Ph.D. Candidate in Computer Science and Engineering

Aug 2019 - Present

Lab: Rigorous Design Lab, UTA
 Advisor: Mohammad Atiqul Islam

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (BUET), Dhaka, Bangladesh

B.S. in Electrical and Electronic Engineering

Sept 2018

PROFESSIONAL EMPLOYMENT

Graduate Research Assistant

Computer Science and Engineering, The University of Texas at Arlington

Lab: Rigorous Design Lab (RiDL)

Aug 2019 – Current

Graduate Teaching Assistant

Computer Science and Engineering, The University of Texas at Arlington

Notable Courses: Algorithm & Data Structure, Computer Architecture, Profes- Aug 2019 - Current

sional Practices etc

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant

Rigorous Design Lab (RiDL), UTA

Aug 2019 - Current

■ Fair Federated Learning with Heterogeneous Devices

- Proposed algorithms ensure fairness for heterogeneous devices with respect to model architecture for federated learning
- Remove local computational power bottlenecks among participating clients in federated learning
- Incorporate Q-fairness among clients to minimize the variance of accuracy among clients
- Proposed the theoretical analysis of convergence guarantee of fair FL with heterogeneous devices

■ Self Regulating Clients for Federated Learning

- The designed algorithm enables self-regulating clients who can actively take decisions regarding participation in federated learning
- Self-regulating clients can save local computation costs by stopping them from doing local computation
- Self-regulating clients can save uplink communication costs by not sending the model update to the global server
- Proposed algorithm can be incorporated in the backend with any existing federated learning techniques
- Proposed the theoretical analysis of convergence guarantee of fair FL with heterogeneous devices

■ Auto-Weighted Aggregation for Heterogeneous Federated Learning

- The proposed lightweight auto-weighted aggregation techniques can handle the heterogeneity of federated learning by minimizing the weight of unfavorable model updates
- The proposed algorithm is lightweight and adds no additional computation to the global server
- The proposed algorithm is scalable and robust without adding additional computation
- The worst-case performance of the proposed algorithm is like the popular federated averaging techniques

■ Server-Level Power Monitoring in Data Centers Using Single-Point Voltage Measurement

- The proposed power monitoring approach extracts power consumption information of all servers by utilizing the conducted electromagnetic interference of server power supplies
- This is a low-cost approach and needs only one sensor
- Designed the prototype to get the voltage information
- Real-time power monitoring is possible using the side channel information

PUBLICATIONS

Refereed Journal Papers

- Zahidur Talukder, Mohammad A. Islam, "Remote Access Attack for Active Sensors in Autonomous Vehicles", [In Submission]
- Sajedul Talukder, Md. Iftekharul Islam Sakib, Zahidur Talukder, "Giving Up Privacy For Security: A Survey
 On Privacy Trade-off During Pandemic Emergency", International Journal on Cryptography and Information
 Security (IJCIS), Jul 2020.
- Sajedul Talukder and **Zahidur Talukder**, "A Survey on Malware Detection and Analysis Tools", International Journal of Network Security & Its Applications (IJNSA), Vol. 12, No. 2, Mar 2020.
- Zahidur Talukder, "A comparative study of various methods of Phasor Measurement Unit (PMUs)", Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (BUET), 2018.

Refereed Conference Papers

- Zahidur Talukder, Bingqian Lu, Mohammad A. Islam, Shaolei Ren, "Fair Federated Learning with Heterogeneous Devices", [In Submission]
- Zahidur Talukder, Mohammad A. Islam, "FedSRC: Efficient Federated Learning with Self-Regulating Clients", ACM International Conference on Measurement and Modeling of Computer Systems (SIGMETRICS), 2022 (Poster).
- Zahidur Talukder, Mohammad A. Islam, "Computationally Efficient Auto-Weighted Aggregation for Heterogeneous Federated Learning", IEEE International Conference on Edge Computing Communications (IEEE EDGE), 2022.
- Zahidur Talukder, Kazi Nishat, Md Shamim Reza, "A Comparative Study of Various Methods of Phasor Measurement Unit Algorithms", 1st International Conference on Advances in Science, Engineering and Robotics Technology (ICASERT), 2019.
- Sajedul Talukder, Md. Iftekharul Islam Sakib, Md. Faruk Hossen, **Zahidur Talukder** and Md. Shohrab Hossain, "Attacks and Defenses in Mobile IP: Modeling with Stochastic Game Petri Net", In Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Current Trends in Computer, Electrical, Electronics and Communication (**IEEE ICCTCEEC**), Sep 2017.
- Sajedul Talukder, Md. Iftekharul Islam Sakib, Zahidur Talukder, Upoma Das, Arnob Saha and Nur Sultan Nazar Bayev, "USenSewer: Ultrasonic Sensor and GSM-Arduino Based Automated Sewerage Management", In Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Current Trends in Computer, Electrical, Electronics and Communication (IEEE ICCTCEEC), Sep 2017.

Workshops and Posters

- Pranjol Gupta, Zahidur Talukder, Mohammad A. Islam, Phuc Nguyen, "Towards Server-Level Power Monitoring in Data Centers Using Single-Point Voltage Measurement", 20th ACM Conference on Embedded Networked Sensor Systems (SenSys), 2022.
- Zahidur Talukder, Mohammad A. Islam, "FedSRC: Efficient Federated Learning with Self-Regulating Clients", ACM International Conference on Measurement and Modeling of Computer Systems (SIGMETRICS), 2022 (Poster).

■ Zahidur Talukder, Mohammad A. Islam, "FedASL: Auto Weighted Aggregation Techniques for Federated Learning", SCRF@UTA 2022, Best Poster Award Honorable Mention.

WORK IN PROGRESS

- Zahidur Talukder, Bingqian Lu, Mohammad A. Islam, Shaolei Ren, "Fair Federated Learning with Heterogeneous Devices", In preparation.
- Zahidur Talukder, Mohammad A. Islam, "Self Regulating clients for Federated Learning", In preparation.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Graduate Teaching Assistant

Department of Computer Science and Engineering, UTA

Aug 2019 - Present

- CSE-4323-001-QUANTITATIVE COMPUTER ARCH
 - Designed weekly quizzes, graded quizzes, and lab reports, and tracked the students' progress using Gradescope and Canvas
 - Provided students with one-on-one tutoring and regular out-of-class assistance
 - Tutored students with special needs, including those with learning disabilities or who had language disadvantages
- CSE-3318-001-ALGORITHMS DATA STRUCTURES
 - Assisted professor with classroom instruction materials, exams, assignments, and record keeping
 - Collaborated with the professor at the weekly meetings and actively contributed new ideas on teaching
 - Improved student participation in the classroom through integration of creative role-playing exercises and peer review sessions
- CSE-4314-001-PROFESSIONAL PRACTICES
 - Prepared and presented lectures using multimedia technologies such as Zoom, PowerPoint, video clips, and Canvas course website
 - Developed and graded exams and quizzes that assess student mastery of subject matter
- CSE-5392-001-TOPICS IN COMPUTER SCIENCE
 - Prepared lesson plans, and assignments and conducted the labs
 - Evaluated homeworks, tests, and quizzes and held office hours to ensure students understood course concepts
 - Consistently received positive teacher evaluations from students
- CSE-1105-001-INTRO COMPUTER SCI ENGR
 - Conducted labs and graded student lab reports and quizzes using Canvas
 - Held office hours to ensure students understood the labs and successfully balanced student work-load with teaching work-load

MENTORING EXPERIENCE

OurCS@DFW Team Presentation Mentor

- [Security-H] Stealing Secret Data from Computers Without a Network (Best OurCS@DFW Team Presentation Awards)
 - Conduct the workshop in Computer science in the Dallas, Fort Worth area with more than 6 undergraduate students
 - Provided students hardware and software facilities to build their own project

UTA LSAMP - Summer Research Academy Mentor

- Social Impact of Machine learning and AI
 - Mentor an undergraduate student to learn about the social impact of Machine learning and Al
 - Help her to explore the potential privacy and security aspects of AI in our society

Summer High School Student Mentor

- Introduction to Machine learning and AI
 - Mentor a High school student to learn about Machine learning and Al
 - Provided all the materials to a high-level understanding of the concept of machine learning and Al
 - Teach a few machine learning algorithms, like clustering, PCA, ICA, and tree

HONORS AND AWARDS

- Best Poster Award Honorable Mention, SCRF@UTA, 2022
- Dean's Merit List Award from Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (BUET), 2017 & 2018
- Honorable Mention in Undergraduate Thesis Poster Competition, Department of EEE, BUET, 2018
- Bangladesh Government Merit Scholarship, Secondary and Higher Secondary public exams (Top 1% among 2 million students), 2011 & 2013

REFERENCES

Available upon request.